如果通过塞萨利撤退到岸边
Perhaps if we retreat to the coast via Thessaly
我们可以坚持到大雨来临的时候
we could hold out until the rains come.
如果我们往东边走，他们会在这拦截我们
If we go eastward, they'll be able to cut us off here.
噢，对…
Oh, of course.
这样行不通
It will not do.
准备好了
Ready.
如果你期待着地图给你想个法子出来
Maps never redraw themselves,
那我劝你还是早点打消这个念头吧
if that's what you're waiting for.
他说的对
He's right.
我们不如就在这里决一死战
We shall just have to fight the wretches here where we stand.
打败他们
And beatthem.
放心吧，我们会赢的
Oh, we shall crush them, doubtless.
兵不刃血，让他们都去死吧
Dinner for worms, the whole damn lot of 'em.
兵不刃血
Dinner for worms.
这次可别刮出血来了
Try to avoid bloodshed this time.
总比庞贝来为您刮好一些
Wait a while and Pompey can shave you instead.
托卡图斯应该有个一官半职
Torquatus should have something, no?
当个执政官什么的
A Praetorship perhaps.
如果托卡图斯当上高官
If Torquatus is given high office,
瓦罗也得给个官衔，否则有的可闹了
then varro must be given same, else we'll see no end of trouble.
那么我们给莱比耶纳斯什么东西呢？
But then what do we give Labienus?
马其顿？  比斯欣尼亚给他，马其顿给里伯
Macedonia?  Bythnia. Macedonia to Libo.
厚此薄彼，徇私么？
Plums for your people and porridge for the rest, eh?
马其顿和比斯欣尼亚还不是我们的领土
Macedonia and Bythnia are not yet ours to bestow.
你这是在异想天开
You are cooking rabbits that have not been caught.
我们的猎物已经无路可退，饥肠辘辘
Our particular rabbit is cornered, starving,
损失了近2,000人
and has lost near 2,000 men.
我想我们可以这么说
I think we may safely say
这场仗是赢定了
that here is a rabbit ready for the pot.
为什么闷闷不乐，布鲁图斯？  噢，是吗？
Why so melancholy, Brutus?  Oh, do I seem so?
请原谅
Mmm.  Forgive me.
击败恺撒是无上的光荣
No, Caesar's defeat is a glory--
我们已经不能再忍受暴政了 但我高兴不起来
we cannot endure tyrants- but I cannot celebrate it.
他对我来说如同父亲
He was as my father to me.
我同情你，我们什么时候进攻？
I feel for you. When do we strike?
进攻？进攻早就开始了
Strike? We have already struck.
我们包围了他，但他还没死，不是吗？
We have him down, but he is not dead yet, eh?
我们什么时候给他最后的一击？  我们不会
When do we strike the final blow?  There will not be one.
我们只需要继续困住他一个月
If we simply keep him bottled up a month or so more,
他剩下的部队就会彻底崩溃
the remains of his army will disintegrate and disappear,
不需要我们出手  这样做有什么荣誉可言？
at no cost to us.  Is that honorable?
恺撒迫使我们离开罗马
Mmm?  Caesar has driven us from Rome,
让我们背井离乡，杀害我们的朋友
chased us out of ltaly, killed our friends,
霸占我们的国家
usurped our Republic.
屈辱必须用血才能洗清
Surely, dignity and honor demands we walk in his blood.
完全同意
Certainly, knee deep.
但你却让饥饿为我们代劳
But you would have hunger do our work for us!
我们应该主动进攻把恺撒活活的烧死
We must attack Caesar and kill him under the eyes of Mars,
否则胜利毫无意义  他说的有道理
else our victory is empty.  He has sense.
我们要斩草除根
It will look better at home if we win by force.
你可是庞贝·麦格纳斯
You are Pompey Magnus.
你所向披靡，敌人对你来说如同蝼蚁一般
You conquer and crush your enemies as if they were insects.
人们看到您现在的做法会失望的
People will be disappointed by anything less.
希腊来的消息
News from Greece.
马克·安东尼很安全
Mark Antony is safe, but most of the ships in his fleet
但是被派去帮助恺撒，恺撒的舰队大部分沉没
sent in aid of Gaius Julius Caesar have been lost at sea.
恺撒已经被重重包围
Caesar is now surrounded and severely outnumbered.
庞贝·麦格纳斯及其上议院
The forces of the Republic and Senate
自信的认为
and of Pompey Magnus confidently expect
胜利已经不可逆转
a decisive victory to follow shortly.
原来你在这  我在这
There you are.  Here I am.
我找泰门让他来保护我们
I ask Timon for protection,
他却派了一队老弱病残来
and he sends me a bunch of half wits and clowns!
真让我感到惊讶  恺撒随时可能会死
Dear me.  Caesar will soon be dead
我们就没有靠山了
by every account, and we shall be undefended.
我们可能会落魄街头
We may as well be lying naked in the street!
你必须去找赛维莉娅让她派点人手过来
You must go to Servilia and ask for a few of her men
保护我们  为什么？
to stand outside for us.  Why?
这样就可以以她的名义保护我们，小傻瓜
So that they can guard our doors in her name, silly.
我是说为什么要我去？
I mean why must I go?
你难道认为我会去找赛维莉娅求情吗？
Well, as if I would go begging to Servilia.
别说笑了  我可不想去为了你求情
I think not.  I'll not go begging for you.
别孩子气了，她又不会拒绝你
Oh, don't be so childish. It's not as if she'll refuse.
只是你的想法罢了  她有什么理由拒绝你呢？
You think?  Why would she?
我送她那么多可爱的礼物
Those lovely gifts I gave her?
她是不是说了些什么？  没什么
What did she say?  Nothing.
没说什么… 她一定说了些什么
Nothing.  She said something.
她什么都没说
She said nothing.
你很无知，知道吗？
You're very arrogant, that's all.
以为可以通过一些奴隶和乌龟就能买到她的友谊
Think you can buy her friendship with stud slaves and tortoises?
还有六桶冰块
And sixbarrelsofice.
我不想去
I'd rather not go.
你不想去？
You'd rather not go.
难道你宁愿被那些下等人侵犯？
You'd rather be gang-raped by slavering proles
眼睁睁看着你母亲的房子被焚毁？
while your mother's house burns down around you.
老实说，我不在乎
Frankly, I'm past caring.
当恺撒在的时候你就趾高气昂
One day Caesar is winning and you crow happily,
当他失败的时候我却必须去开始低声下气的求人
next day he is losing, and I must go a-begging?
我只希望这场愚蠢的战争早点结束
I just want this vile war to be over,
越快越好  奥克塔维娅，战争已经结束了
one way or the other.  Octavia, it is over.
这就是为什么你必须去找赛维莉娅的原因
That is why you must go to Servilia's house.
我知道这让人难堪，但我们没有其他办法了
It's a bore, I know, but there we are.
莱蒂
Lyde.
真漂亮
very nice.
别过来…
Don't.
见到你真高兴
I'm glad to see you.
我一直在担心你
I've been worried about you.
让你费心了
No need.
我过的很好
I'm doing very well.
不过显然，你过的更好
Not as well as you, obviously.
你需要钱吗？
Do you need money?
如果你需要，我还有点钱
I've got money if you need some.
你当然有钱
I'm sure you have.
背叛你的丈夫，嫁给了有钱人
Turns out your man backed the right horse.
有钱人都喜欢你
Fortune loves you.
我甚至都不知道乌瑞纳斯是不是还活着
I don't know if Vorenus is alive or dead.
对不起…
I'm sorry.
对不起
我并不想这样的
I didn't want to be like this.
我已经厌倦了，内奥比
I'm so tired, Niobe.
我厌倦了憎恨
I'm tired of being angry.
我无法让自己继续
I'm tired of...
恨着你
hating you.
我只剩下你一个人可以依靠了
You're all I've got.
对不起
I'm sorry.
要来点糖水吗？
Do you want some honey water?
你在浪费时间
You're wasting your time!
在我们饿死之前，我们早就渴死了
We'll die of thirst long before we die of hunger.
我们可以喝他们的血
We could drink their blood.
你说什么？  那些死人
Repeat?  All these dead men,
我们可以喝他们的血
we can drink their blood.
盐分太多
Too salty.
只会让你更想喝水
Only make you more thirsty.
而且尸体都已经腐烂了
Putrid by now anyway.
没关系
Doesn't matter.
一切都会好起来的
Everything will be fine.
这就是我们的死地了
This is where we die.
你在写什么？
What are you writing?
给内奥比的留言
A message to Niobe.
好吧
All right.
是个好主意
Good idea.
也给帮我给艾瑞纳留个言吧，如果可以的话
Send my best to Eirene, will you, while you're at it?
如果还有地方可写…
If there's space.
格瑞丝，我们看起来漂亮极了，不是吗？
Graces, don't we look lovely.
如果我是一个乞求者，我可不会打扮成这样
If I am to be a beggar, I will not look like one.
噢，我可不是在指责什么，亲爱的
Oh, I am not objecting, my honey,
尽管你会让赛维莉娅知道她已经人老珠黄了
though you will remind Servilia of what an old trout she has become.
我很高兴你可以打扮的这么漂亮
I'm just happy to see you looking so pretty for once.
你过去总是很邋遢
You do so often insist on playing the frump.
祝你的母亲过的好  她过的很好
I hope your mother thrives.  She does.
您儿子呢？  他也很好
And your son?  Also.
我的母亲让我来请求您的帮助
My mother sends me to ask a favor.  Mm-hmm?
她害怕希腊的战争结果
She fears the consequences
会带来灾难
of this last battle in Greece.
可以理解
Understandably.
她过惯了无忧无虑的日子
She has enjoyed her ascendancy a little too well.
她想从您这借点人手
She asks you to lend her some men
以您的名义保护我们的家产
to protect our door in your name.
当然可以
Of course.
艾伦尼，派阿贾克斯去
Eleni, send Ajax and three or four others,
再带几个他信的过的人手  谢谢
whoever he thinks best.  Thank you.
很感激您的慷慨
It's very kind of you. I told my mother
我告诉过我母亲她不应该… 别这么说
she should not presume-  Please.
这都是她应得的
She shall have what she needs.
对不起，您对我们实在非常照顾
Forgive me. You are so good to us.
我们不值得您这样做  别这么说
We do not deserve it.  Don't.
我…我一定看起来糟透了
I mu- I must look a fright.
不，一点也不
No, not really.
你看起来很可爱
You look lovely.
我还是回家吧
I better go home.
这么快？
So soon?
我母亲会担心的
My mother will be worried.
好吧，如果你认为如此的话…
Well, if you feel you should.
奥克塔维娅…
Octavia...
谢谢
Thank you.
给罗马送个信
Send to Rome.
告诉他们…
Tell them...
决定性的战役…
the decisive battle
今天开打…
begins today.
长官！庞贝的军团已经准备好了
Sir! Pompey's legions are in the field in battle array!
谢谢，福利维奥，不过你忘了敬礼，不是吗？
Thank you, Fulvio. Have you forgotten how to salute?
没有，长官，请原谅，长官
I haven't, sir. No excuse, sir.
格雷科斯，马上过来
Gracchus, sound assembly!
把我的马准备好  是，长官！
Have Xeno saddle my horse.  Sir!
我们接受开战？
We will accept battle?
当然，为什么不？
Certainly. Why not?
我们人数上没有任何优势
We are outnumbered
步兵数是他们的三分之一，骑兵只有他们的五分之一
three to one on foot and five to one on horse.
没受伤的士兵们
What uninjured men we have
也快被饥饿和绝望打倒…
are scared and hungry and desperate.
这也是为什么我们具有破釜沉舟的准备
That is the advantage we must press home.
嘴巴不能用来打仗
I was not aware irony had military usage.
获胜或者死，只有一条路可走
We must win or die.
庞贝的士兵可没有视死如归
Pompey's men have other options.
再见，伯斯卡
Goodbye, Posca.
恺撒！恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
给罗马送个信
Send to Rome.
告诉他们恺撒赢了
Tell them Caesar has won.
长官！恺撒的士兵们追来了
Sir! Caesar's men are coming!
我把我的手割破了
I've cut my hand.
我们必须快走，长官，他们会俘虏您的
We have to go, sir! They'll catch you.
不是很深的伤口，却很痛
It's not deep, but it hurts.
他们会杀了您的！！
They will kill you!
都无所谓了…
It's of no consequence.
我们的部队都失败了，现在怎么办？
Our forces are routed. What are we to do?
择日再战，这还用说吗？
We shall fight again another day I do not doubt...
然后击败他们  然后…击败他们
And prevail! -...and prevail.
但现在，我们必须先保证自己的安全
But for the present we must look to our safety.
我们的安危毫不足惜
Our safety is nothing.
我们必须离开希腊，重新招募新兵
We must leave Greece and look to fresh levies.
我倒想问问我们能去哪？  非洲
And may one ask where?  Africa.
我们必须在非洲重整旗鼓
We must rally the cities of Africa.
非洲，我的上帝啊
Africa. Dear gods,
这样下去很快我们就会无处可去
we are fast running out of continents.
还会失去金钱！
And coin!
我们已经榨干了希腊人民的最后一点血汗
We have taxed every last coin from Greece
现在都已经花完了
and spent it all.
我们凭什么让非洲人归顺于我们？
What shall we use to buy Africa's loyalty?
用贝壳吗？  我们什么都不需要买
Seashells?  We need buy nothing!
我们可是罗马的上议院
We are the Senate of Rome!
我们只是一群鞋上沾满泥土的老头
We are old men with mud on our shoes!
只要我们还有一口气，我们就没有失败
We are not beaten until we are dead.
共和国与我们同在
The Republic lives as long as we do!
你自己去打仗吧
You may fight on as you wish.
我…
Asforme,
我要去向恺撒投降
I will go from here and surrender myself to Caesar.
难道你没有尊严和荣誉感吗？
Have you no dignity? No honor?
也许有那么一点
Some little I hope.
但没有你那么多
Not so much as you of course.
恺撒会杀了你的  也许会的
Caesar will kill you.  That may be.
但我不怕死
I'm not afraid to die.
我已经厌倦了
I'm tired.
我只想回家
I want to go home.
对，我的想法也是如此
Yes. My feelings exact.
布鲁图斯，以你的名字向上帝起誓…
Brutus, without the force of your name, the cause of the Re--
不！别和我谈什么共和国
Do not! Do not talk to me of the Republic.
如果我知道我是身处在
If I had known what wretched company
一个如此腐朽，堕落，迂腐的国家
and rotten food I would endure,
如果我知道庞贝是这样的一个蠢老头
if I had known what an old fool is Pompey,
我绝不会离开罗马
I would never have left Rome.
请原谅我的失礼
Forgive my anger.
我刚才有些过火了  别放在心上
I am not myself.  Think nothing of it.
我原谅你的不敬
I merit your disappointment.
我提议我们去菲波里
I propose we make for Amphipoli.
我在那有钱和人力
I have men and money there,
我们可以从那坐船去埃及
and we can go by sea to Egypt.
托勒密的孩子都是我的生死之交
Ptolemy's children are loyal friends of mine.
也许…
Perhaps...
Perhaps it's better
我们最好分道扬镳
we do not travel together.
也许你是对的
Perhaps you're right.
毫无疑问
Better.
这样好一些…
No doubt.
我不明白
I don't understand it.
至少该发生点什么
Something should have turned up by now.
我不应该就这么死了
I'm not meant to die this way.
我想你理解错了  不应该是这样的
You were misinformed.  Doesn't seem right.
至少…
Still...
去天堂里还能再见到我母亲
it'd be good to see my mother again.
你认为他们会有安排吗？
Do you think they have a system
为那些寻找亲人的家伙准备的？  什么？
for finding people?  What?
你死了以后，怎么去找到你想要找的人呢？
In the afterlife- how do you go about finding people?
一定有很多死人… 一定的…
There must be millions of them.  Must be.
也许她已经认不出我了
She won't recognize me, probably.
她死的时候我还很小…
I was very young when she died.
也许我会让她吓一跳，不是吗？
Probably give her a big scare though, huh?
一个高大，丑陋，残忍的家伙朝她走过去拥抱她…
Big, ugly brute coming along and giving her a hug.
看那  什么？
Look at that.  What?
那具尸体
That corpse.
看到他在水中飘着了吗？
See how high it rides in the water?
海水把他泡的膨胀了起来
The plutonic aether inflates him.
那又如何？
What of it?
你不是喝海水喝了糊涂了吧？
You've not been drinking seawater, have you?!
亲爱的，吃点吧  噢，对
Husband, eat.  Oh, yeah.
在那，亲爱的
Over here, my dear.
来，吃吧
Here.
有点咸  不会啊，味道很好不是吗？
Little salty.  Not at all. It's good, neh?
非常好吃，妈妈
Delicious, Mama.
亲爱的，你吃的脸上都是
Bona Dea, look at your faces.
噢，小傻瓜
Oh, sillies.
海伦？
Helen?
海伦
Helen!
亲爱的，醒醒，我们的人都走了
Husband, wake up! Our people are leaving.
来吧，宝贝们，别害怕
Now now, my darlings. Don't be scared.
我们来玩个游戏吧
We're on an adventure, eh?
第一个看到海并且喊出来的人
The first one to see the sea and cry out
当我们到了菲波里时，就给他一个桃子
will have a peach when we get to Amphipoli.
你，再说一次你的名字
You, your name again?
里桑德罗斯  里桑德罗斯，距离菲波里还有多远？
Lysandros.  Lysandros, how far to Amphipoli?
噢，非常近，非常近
Oh, very close. Close.
我们按照原计划继续前进
We will continue there as planned.
你不能随便向行人透露我的身份
You're not to announce my identity to those that we meet.
如果他们问起来呢？
And if they ask?
梅拉
Mella.
埃尼亚斯·梅拉  明白，长官
Aeneas Mella.  Hear and obey, Captain.
那谁付钱给我们呢？
And who'll pay?
付钱？
Pay?
你们不是早就拿到报酬了吗？
You've been paid already.
那是带路的费用，现在又要增加保护费用
For guiding, not for protection.
我有很多人和物资
I have many men and supplies
还有大笔的钱在菲波里
and ample coin in Amphipoli.
到了那你就可以拿到报酬  你身边没有钱吗？银币什么的？
You will be paid there.  None with you now? Coin?
没有！！我不会再容忍你的任何不敬举动
None! I'll tolerate no more of your impudence!
请原谅，长官，只是问问
No disrespect, Captain. Only asking.
我们出发
We go.
你的喋喋不休都快把我逼疯了
You drive me insane with your wretched muttering.
你整天都在和你的神唠叨些什么？
What is wrong that you must harass the gods so?
没什么
Nothing.
那就停止吧
Well, stop it then.
赛维莉娅邀请你明天和她一起编织
Servilia sends to invite you to weave with her tomorrow.
我不想去  你必须去，我已经答应了
I cannot.  Of course you can.
我不想去  我知道她很乏味
I've already accepted.  I cannot!
噢，不，我是说编织
I know she's tedious. I mean really, weaving,
但目前来说，我们必须让她满意
but we must keep her happy for the time being.
但是…
But--
海！海！
The sea! The sea!
异口同声！你们每个人都会得到一个桃子作为奖赏
Unison. You shall both have a peach.
看，妈妈，死人
Look, Mama. Dead people.
味道还不错吧？
It's good, huh?
你们从哪来？
Where do you come from?
布林迪西
Brindisi.
罗马人
Romans?
我认识你
I know you.
我在哪见过你？
Where do I know you from?
我想我们并不认识
I have not seen you before.
我肯定在哪见过你
I'm sure I've seen you somewhere.
把水和面包留给他们，我们继续赶路
Leave them water and bread, we need to be going.
把他们丢下？他们很虚弱
Leave them? Weak as they are?
我已经没有时间了
I have no time to waste.
马上就要天黑了
Soon be dark anyhow.
我们在这扎营，明天早上就能到菲波里
We camp here, get to Amphipoli in the morning.
我们必须坚持赶路
I insist we go on.
放松点吧，老人家
Relax, old man.
我们会到的
We get there.
你们好好休息吧，伙计们
You rest easy now, boys.
吃点东西，恢复体力
Eat, drink, get your strength back.
我们会成为好朋友的
You and me will be good friends.
嘿！你难道要我追着你的屁股后面
Hey! You want my cock up you
才会好好干活，生一堆火起来吗？
or are you going to build a damn fire?
我就说我们会没事的吧
I told you we'd be all right.
不用担心的
There's no pleasing some.
我们在这扎营？
We stop here?
为什么这么早？
Why so early?
我想最好是这样…马上就要天黑了
Best to, I think. It'll be dark soon.
他们是谁？  我怎么知道？！
Who are they?  How should I know?
他们是谁不管我的事？
Who cares who they are?
对不起，对不起…
Sorry. Sorry.
我…
I--
一切都会好起来的
all will be well,
我向你保证
I assure you.
一切都会好起来的
Allwill bewell.
庞贝·麦格纳斯
Pompey Magnus.
那个人长的很像庞贝·麦格纳斯
That man looks exactly like Pompey Magnus.
我就说我在什么地方看到过他
That's why I thought I'd met him.
别用手指！
Don't point.
这不可能  简直不敢相信，不是吗？
Never.  It's hard to believe, eh?
他的妻子和孩子也在这里
His wife and sprouts too.
恺撒会赏给我们多少黄金啊？
Caesar's going to drown us in gold.
Cac!
我们该怎么办？
What do we do?
我不知道…
I don't know yet.
感谢你能来
Thank you for coming.
是母亲坚持要这么做
Mother insisted.
我听说您想和我一起做编织
I understand you want me to do some weaving with you.
抱歉让你感到不安
I'm sorry you are upset.
上次的事情…
The last time we saw each other--
没有关系…
It's of no consequence.
你喜欢编织吗？
Are you fond of weaving?
我也是
So did l.
你的兄长怎么样？
And how is your brother?
他还是住在米狄欧兰侬？  是的
Is he still in Mediolanum?  He is.
我听说那很不错
Lovely town, so I'm told.
空气非常好  多米那？
Healthy air.  Domina?
什么事情，艾伦尼？
What is it, Eleni?
希腊来了消息了
Word from Greece.
恺撒赢了
Caesar has won.
庞贝的军队被彻底击跨了
And Pompey's armies are completely destroyed.
我的儿子呢？
And my son?
没有消息…
No word.
别哭！
Don't cry.
Oh.
以罗马的名义，停下！
Halt! In the name of Rome!
现在称他们自己为罗马了？真不知羞耻
Calls himself Rome, now, does he? Shameless.
你们是谁？目的是什么？
Who are you and what's your purpose?
我们是罗马人，孩子
We are Rome, boy,
战败的那些…
what's left of it.
来向你的长官投降
Come to surrender to your chief.
布鲁图斯
Brutus!
西赛罗
Cicero!
见到你们真高兴
How happy I am to see you.
我还以为你死了
I thought you were dead.
陛下，我…
Sir, l--
我虔诚的到来
I am come here honorably,
恳求您的宽恕
with no request for mercy,
收留我的士兵和马匹
to surrender my arms and my horses
同时… 嘘！我们别说投降了
as is-  Ssh. We'll have no talk of surrender.
我们只是吵了一架，现在我们又是朋友了，不是吗？
We've merely quarreled a little. Now we are friends again, eh?
感激您的宽容…
That is most generous of you
以及您的男子气概
and natural to your manly nature,
but I cannot-  My poor boy.
对不起，我很抱歉
I'm sorry. I am so sorry.
Not at all.
是我的错
It is I am sorry.
是我让你陷入了两难的处境
I presented you with an impossible dilemma.
你只是做了你应该做的事情
You did only what you thought honorable,
我相信你
I'm sure.
用我的吻来化解这一切
I kiss you for it.
谢谢
Thank you.
我永远不会忘记的
I will not forget this grace.
以我最诚挚的敬意…
As I was saying, a most generous-  But what of Pompey?
庞贝呢？告诉我他还活着
Tell me he lives.
他还活着…
He lives.
感谢上帝，他在哪？
Thank the gods. Where is he?
He...
他…他并不打算投降…
He does not plan to surrender.
这太疯狂了…
That is insane.
他无处藏身，他能逃到哪去？
He cannot escape. Where can he go?
西比乌和他在一起吗？卡托呢？
Is Scipio with him? Cato?
他们逃到非洲去了
They have fled to Africa.
我都在想些什么呀…
What am I thinking of...
在你们饥肠辘辘的时候问你们这些
asking you questions when you must be so hungry and thirsty?
来吧
Come.
我想我最好… 别说其他的
I think I would rather-  I insist.
来吧
Come.
我这只手正忙着呢
So with this hand, otherwise engaged
我只好用我的拳头打那个小兔崽子
I had to take that worm and beat him
一拳，一拳，不停的打
with my fists over and over and over again!
他的父亲托勒密·奥利提斯12世国王
His father King Ptolemy Auletes the 1 2th
是我的好朋友
was a close friend of mine.
他总是热情的邀请我去那
I was always assured a loving welcome
在埃及，我记得有一次
in Egypt. I remember on one occasion
我和国王一起出去打猎
I was out hunting with the King.
我们在追捕狮子，你们知道吗？
We were hunting lions, you see.
但这个国王的箭法非常糟糕
Only the King was rather a poor bowman,
我们都不知道这头狮子是不是死了…
and we couldn't tell if the lion was wounded or dead.
嘿，伙计们
Hello, friends.
感觉好些了吗？有力气了吗？
Feeling better, neh? Strong?
力量十足
Strong enough.
告诉我点消息吧，那个罗马人叫什么名字？
Tell me something. What's the name of that Roman?
他叫…
His name is, uh,
埃尼亚斯·梅拉
Aeneas Mella.
他是这么说的
That's what he said.
你听说过恺撒和庞贝吗？
What do you hear of Caesar and Pompey?
我知道，他们在打仗
They fought, I heard.
然后呢？
And?
你们当然知道谁赢了
You know who won.
告诉我们吧
Tell us.
Pfft!
我已经打算让你们入伙
I was going to let you in anyway.
他在说什么？  得了，我知道你们是聪明的小伙子
What's he talking about?  You boys are clever fellows, I bet.
你们知道如何战斗，对吧？
Know how to fight.
我和我的伙计们搞不定他们
Me and my boys can't take his people alone.
我可以让你们入伙，没问题的
Us and you together, no problem.
我们平分奖金
We go down middle on the reward.
不错的主意
Not a bad idea.
你们可以拥有他的妻子和孩子
You can have the wife and children,
我把他的奴隶带走
I take the slaves.
走开
Walk away...
别再和我说这些  好吧
and do not speak of this again.  I see.
你以为你们可以甩掉我？
Think you don't need me, eh?
想独吞奖金吗？
Think you can keep the reward for yourself?
见鬼去吧，门都没有  闭嘴
Fuck you. Not going to happen.  Don't.
去死吧！我给了你们重生
Fuck you! I gave you your lives back,
我也可以随时让你们去死
I can take them away again, easy.
当我说完了以后
When I am finished speaking,
你就转身走
you will turn and run
那边  那边？
that way.  That way?
不如这儿怎么样？
What about this way?
别让我再看到你
Do not stop until you are out of my sight
也别回头，否则我宰了你
and do not delay, or I will kill you.
他是怎么回事？
What is wrong with him?
我已经说完了
I am finished speaking.
他说话有点难听，不是吗？
A bit harsh, isn't it?
我认为他提供的交易值得考虑
Fair enough deal he was offering, I thought.
你们这是干什么？  先生…
What is the meaning of this?  Sir--
回答！这个人是我雇佣的
Speak up! This man was in my employ!
他策划攻击你  你又怎么知道？
He planned to assault you.  How do you know?
他打算拉我们入伙
He asked us to participate.
然后你就拒绝了，为了我而杀了他
You refused, stabbed him to death on my behalf.
真是个够朋友的陌生人啊！！
A good friend to me on such short acquaintance.
你叫什么名字？  卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
What is your name?  I am Lucius vorenus.
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒麾下的13军伊瓦卡提团的长官
Prefect and Evocati of the 13th Legion of Galius Julius Caesar.
泰特斯·波罗，隶属于同一军团
Titus Pullo, legionary of same.
对不起，卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Salve, Lucius vorenus.
我是…
I am...
埃尼亚斯·梅拉
AeneusMella...
帕加马人
of Pergamum.
埃尼亚斯·梅拉
AeneusMella.
你最好明白你现在处于我的管辖之下
You must consider yourself under my charge.
我不明白…
I do not understand.
你是第13军团的囚犯
Consider yourself a prisoner of the 13th Legion.
我只是个商人
I'm just a merchant.
我们知道你是谁，先生
We know who you are, sir.
你们现在都归我管，明白吗？
I own you now! Understand?!
你，你，把他埋了
You, you, bury him.
你们剩下的人
The rest of you...
别让他们跑了  卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
don't let them leave.  Lucius vorenus.
我想私下和你谈谈
I must speak with you alone.
呆在这
Stay here.
我的确没有表明我自己的身份
Of course I do not say I am
你以为我是谁？
who you think I am,
但我在军队中呆过一段时间
but I have spent some years in the army.
也许我们在哪场战役上遇见过
Perhaps we met on some campaign or other.
这也许是我看起来很脸熟的原因
Perhaps that's why I seem familiar.
也许…
Perhaps.
我想起来了，第13军
I recall the 13th...
那是在埃利西亚  是的
was at Alesia.  We were.
我总希望能亲眼目睹那场战斗
There's a battle I've always wished to have seen.
战线拉长到了25公里，是吗？
25 miles of works, wasn't it?
接近30  30？
Nearer 30.  30?
你们有多少人？  60,000
How many men did you have?  60,000.
对付…哇噢
Against- whoa--
几乎是两倍的敌人
almost double the Gauls.
至少是两倍
Atleastdouble.
都是高卢人的勇士
The best men of every tribe in Gaul.
恺撒很会打仗
Caesar can fight.
都是我教给他的
I'll give him that.
我还记得…
I remember...
他在你这个年纪的时候
when he was not much older than you.
我派他去驻守冬季的岗位
I sent him to winter Quarters in--
在…
in, uh...
哪里呢？
Oh, where was it?
都无所谓了
No matter.
是很长时间之前的事情了
Long time gone.
我很想问您，先生，如果允许的话
I must ask you, sir, if I may.
你怎么会落得如此下场？
How did you come to this road?
毫无疑问
Surely...
和庞贝相比，恺撒处于完全劣势
Pompey had Caesar at greater disadvantage.
确实如此
He did.
看起来根本不可能会输
It didn't seem possible to lose.
但那总不是一个好兆头
That's always a bad sign.
战斗是在平原开打
The battlefield was on a plain
在一条河的旁边，一些小山的山脚下
by a river, at the foot of some...Iow hills.
就象这样
Like this, you see.
军队在这里开始短兵相接
The lines met here.
我的部队完全控制了局面
My men held their ground well,
所以我派骑兵
so I sent my horses
到他的右侧去包抄
at his right flank.
看起来非常正确
Which is perfectly correct,
我想你也会同意的  我同意
you'll agree.  I do.
但是这群废物被吓倒了
Only the cowards were repulsed.
是被一队预备兵吓倒的
Repulsed by a single cohort of reserves.
掉头逃跑，200个骑兵
Turned and fled, 200 horses.
直接冲回我的左侧
Crashed directly into my left flank.
把我的阵型冲跨了
Rolled up my line
看起来就象一张地毯
Iike a carpet.
把我的部队完全包围了起来
Put the whole damned army to flight.
所以我战败了…
And here I am.
这就是庞贝·麦格纳斯
That's how Pompey Magnus
如何被打败的
was defeated.
这就是共和国是如何被打败的…
That's how the Republic died.
晚安，先生  等等…
Good night, sir.  Wait.
我不会…
I will not...
我不会为我自己
I will not ask favor
请求什么宽恕
or mercy for myself.
但我请求你
But I beg you...
考虑一下我的…
consider the fate...
妻子和孩子的命运
of my wife and children.
让我把他们带到埃及
Let me take them to Egypt
让他们能在朋友的身边…
where they will be safe...
安全的活下去…
among friends.
请考虑一下…
Consider them.
继续睡吧
Go back to sleep.
简直是不明智而且不道义的行为
Unwise and unfriendly, I call it.
愚蠢而薄情
Unwise and unfriendly.
为什么？
And for why?
Why?
我们已经俘虏了他，我们已经俘虏了他了
We had him. We had him.
马匹，别想什么马匹了
Horses. Never mind, horses.
也别想什么黄金了
Never mind gold.
恺撒会分给我们农田
Caesar would have given us farms
土地，果园和大批的奴隶
and fields and orchards and great flocks of slaves
还有牲口！！如果我们…
and cattle and Dis knows what--
庞贝·麦格纳斯不是那种可以用来换钱的人物
'Sist! Pompey Magnus is no damn slave to be sold for money.
我不明白为什么不？  你不明白的事情多着呢
Don't see why not!  There's a great deal you don't see.
他不明白的事情也多着呢
There's a great deal he doesn't see neither.
你和其他12个人从那场风暴中生还过来了？
You and only 12 other men survived that storm.
5,000个人中只有你们
Out of 5,000.
你能活着一定是背负着巨大的使命
You're being kept alive for some great purpose, no doubt.  Ah, well.
长官…
You know, sir...
他有一些有趣的信息  是吗？
He has some interesting news.  lndeed?
长官，在我们来这的路上
Sir, in course of our journey here,
我们遇上了格涅乌斯·庞贝·麦格纳斯和他的家人
we encountered Gnaeus Pompey Magnus with his family
还有他的仆人  哪里？
and a party of servants.  Where?
在去菲波里的路上，还有一辆骡车
On the road to Amphipoli, with a mule train.
骡车？很贵啊
A mule train. It's priceless.
他打算乘船去埃及，长官
He intends to take ship for Egypt, sir.
家人还是随从，是吗？
Family and servants, you say.
没有士兵？  没有，长官
No soldiers?  None, sir.
一个人都没有留下  一个都没有
Not one man left, not one.
噢，可怜的家伙
Oh, poor wretch.
那么，为什么…
Why then, be that so,
你为什么不俘虏他？  最感人的一段来了
did you not apprehend him?  Now here's the onion.
我认为那样做并不合适
I thought it would be wrong to do so.
解释你的理由
Explain yourself.
他的手在颤抖，长官
His hands trembled, sir.
他的衣服很破败…
His clothes were dirty,
他的眼里含着泪水，他已经彻底垮了
there was water in his eyes- he is broken.
我认为没有必要俘虏他
I saw no need to apprehend him.
我想补充一下，波罗士官
I'd like to add that Legionary Pullo
没有参与这个决定，长官
took no part in my decision, sir.
你认为没有必要
You saw no need.
你没有看到庞贝也许
Do you not see that Pompey may be broken
可以象个落魄的男人一样凄惨，但他还是个危险人物
Iike a Dacian catamite and still be dangerous?
只要他还活着
If he is still living,
敌人就可能在他身边聚集
he will be a standard around which our enemies will gather!
只要他还能骑在马背上
As long as he can be propped on a horse,
他就很危险！
he's dangerous!
但你却认为没有必要俘虏他？  没有必要，长官
But you saw no need to apprehend him?  I did not, sir.
我给你这么大的权力来做这个决定？
Who by the sons of Dis gives you the right to make such judgment?
我知道这是我的失职，长官
Sir, I am aware that I have not done my duty,
但我希望您能告诉我我的过错
and I respectfully ask your pardon.
他要我的解释？
My pardon, he asks.
我应该对你使用鞭刑再把你钉死在十字架上
I ought to have you scourged and crucified.
以后你就会记得
In future you will remember that it is l
只有我可以给予宽恕，没有其他人
that offers mercy. No one else.
明白了吗？
Clear?
明白，长官
Clear, sir.
解散
Dismissed.
我并非有意忤逆您
I do not like to disagree with you,
但您对他太过仁慈了
but you are being far too lenient with him.
他让庞贝跑了您却让他活着？
He let Pompey go and you let him live?!
他应该被当作示众处死！
The man should be made an example of!
其他任何人
Any other man, certainly.
但不是他们两个
But those two...
他们让我想起了一些东西
they found my stolen standard.
他们从一场灾难中存活了下来
Now they survive a wreck
又在海岸边遇上了庞贝
that drowned an army and find Pompey Magnus on a beach.
伟大的神灵在保佑他们
They have powerful gods on their side,
而且我也不会杀死任何有那样义气的朋友的人
and I will not kill any man with friends of that sort.
伯斯卡
Posca.
告诉福利维奥我们要出发了
Tell Fulvio to start breaking camp.
我们去埃及
We're going to Egypt.
尊敬的庞贝先生
General Pompey, sir.
还记得我吗？ 卢西尔斯·萨普提米亚斯
Remember me? Lucius Septimius.
也是百夫长萨普提米亚斯
Centurion Septimius, as was.
我们在西班牙共事过
I was with you in Spain.
第四军，第三团
Fourth legion, third cohort.
卢西尔斯·萨普提米亚斯，当然记得
Lucius Septimius, of course.
你来这干什么？
What are you doing here, of all places?
为埃及人工作，先生
Working for the Gyppoes, sir.  Huh?
我明白，先生，我们已经不是第四军了
I know, sir. It's not the fourth by no means.
但我们必须养活糊口，不是吗？  当然
A man's got to earn his salt, eh?  True enough.
那这些士兵是来干什么的？
What's all this then, soldier?
看起来不象是一个友善的表示
Not much of a welcome party.
你也知道，先生，这是埃及人的做法，可笑的一群人
Oh, you know Egyptians, sir, it's just their way. Funny people.
确实如此
That they are. Well...
老伙计
onward friend.
对不起，长官
I'm sorry, sir.
翻译:TLF字幕组